[Music]
Welcome to the Business Central launch
edition for 2025 release wave 2. This
video is about sales analytics.
According to a recent study from IDC
where they asked a lot of SMB customers
both in the small and medium end of the
segment uh they asked about immediate
business priorities the next 12 months
and the in the top five it was all about
customers sales and profitability. Um,
so it was about growing revenue,
attracting new customers, increase
profitability, improve productivity, and
boost customer loyalty. And what's
common about most of this, if not all,
is that that fits very well into the
area of sales, sales and marketing. So
using both
classic reports and BI or business
intelligence can that both can help you
get a better understanding of the
performance of your sales processes and
hopefully uh also making it possible to
be more datadriven and then accommodate
for those five priorities.
In this wave, we are completing the
modernization of existing reports in
Business Central and also updating the
PowerBI app to help you streamline your
sales organization
specifically for for this area. Um this
is kind of uh what we have achieved. So
updated PowerBI, added Excel layouts for
existing reports, adding Word and and
improving the documentation of all sales
reports.
So for the updated PowerBI app for
sales, three priorities have been uh in
focus. First of all, forecasting
forecasting future sales based on past
uh sales transactions
as well as updating the data model and
reports uh with other types of sales
than selling items. So you can also in
business central sell gines and
resources. So the model is now and the
reports have been enhanced with that.
And the final thing is that we have uh
made the the model and the reports in a
quality where we believe now we can open
source this. So let me show you a little
bit of this in action.
So here in PowerBI I have the updated
app for sales and I want to show you two
new reports pages. If I navigate down to
the last one here, sales forecasting,
this is um utilizing PowerBI
uh PowerBI's forecasting capabilities.
So this is a statistical model. This is
AI but like classic AI or machine
learning. Um so not generative AI. And
uh then uh here you can see a forecast
on your sales amounts um with a trend
line all the way up to June which is
where I kind of set the cutoff. So I
asked uh PowerBI it's based on what you
see from March to June. Please forecast
what's going to happen in the next 3
months.
The forecasting model in PowerBI is very
sophisticated. It can handle uh
seasonality. Uh you can choose the look
back uh look look forward period um and
and other parameters and uh you need if
you need to change our choices of uh for
instance we chose to show an upper a
lower bound and we chose 3 months and uh
probably we had a choice of seasonality
for this. If you have a business that is
operating in a different uh way, you
need to go and change the report visual
and I think I demoed that in detail in
the uh PowerBI for inventory here in the
launch edition. So go watch that video
if you if you want to know how you can
change the the forecasting parameters.
So in um just the starting point of this
is your sales globally. Uh but you can
use the same report to forecast
different things. For instance, if you
have uh here you have a visual that
showcases the distribution of sales
based on your sales staff. So for
instance, if I want to look at the
forecasting based on what Jim did, then
I can filter to that. I could also
filter to a different category. Let's
say I want to forecast uh my furniture
sales. I can filter to that or I can
forecast sales to a particular customer.
Then the forecasting visual just adapts
to that. And of course, anything you can
filter to in the report. uh other things
such as let's say item item down to a
different uh specific item a specific
location and so on um is up for grabs.
So you can filter on that and then
forecast that. So that was forecasting
for sales. Hopefully, you can use this
to be a little bit uh proactive on your
sales instead of only using sales
business intelligence to look at the
past.
The second demo I wanted to show you is
a new report called sales by project and
this is showcasing that the sales app
the model for the sales app is now also
including uh sales from other types than
items. So in this case we have projects
and in projects you can sell resources
and you can sell GL account lines right.
So that means um yeah so you can you
those types of things you can sell is
very prominent here in the sales by
project uh report. This is a new report
but uh but that type um dimension um is
present in all the sales reports where
it makes sense either as a filter or
shown directly in the report visuals.
The final thing is uh open source. So if
I'm have installed the app uh then I can
simply choose file and then download
this file. Note that this only works in
the version 27 in the one we release
here in October. Doesn't work for sales
for the sales app for previous versions
of the PowerBI app for sales. But here
you download uh choose download and then
you get the P the source code PBX file
for the for the app both the report
visuals and the semantic models or the
semantic model.
So the second pillar of our investments
in sales analytics
uh is that we modernized the existing
analytical reports for sales the
built-in reports in business central and
we did two things uh we modernized
meaning that we changed or introduced
new layouts in excel maybe word um and
that allows you as a user to change the
layout to whatever things uh you want as
long as the the data is present in the
report data model and then we improved
help both in client and uh articles in
the Microsoft help documentation.
So this is just one example of many uh
the customer item sales report. Uh this
is uh how it looked in the past from the
PDF output. Um, and with the word
layout, if you still need to print this
report, it kind of looks the same. So,
it doesn't feel like a breaking change
even though we change the technology
behind the rendering of that PDF.
However, if you then instead of using
the word layout use Excel, now you
actually have a fully interactive way of
analyzing that report data set. Um, in
this report, uh, there's only like we
have a printable worksheet and an an
analytical worksheet in the in the Excel
workbook. Um, but think about this in
traditionally the customer item sales
report was kind of showcasing
like grouped by customer what are the
items they bought. But now when things
are in Excel, you could take this report
and just pivot the other way around. So
you could show items by customer and
just create a variation of this layout
and upload it and now or maybe even have
both layouts present. Uh and then you
have kind of a a dual report. So that's
one of the benefits both of having Excel
because you have self-service you can do
that in Excel but also Excel allows you
to have these multiple worksheets with
um each worksheet catering for a
different an analytical scenario. So
here's an example of the inclient help
and the documentation. So any of these
reports have what we call a teaching
tip. If you choose the caption here, you
get a little description. If you choose
help or just have the help pane open,
you get the same uh thing here as well
as a link to documentation. There are
actually more benefits than the help
pane for this. We reuse those
descriptions both in a new advanced
tellme and also in uh in the co-pilot
chat. So this kind of uh is a place
where we have a description defined one
place and it's surfacing many places in
the product. If you choose the report
documentation link here, you get I I
don't have a screenshot of that, but you
would then get an article in Microsoft
learn with both this use case, but also
what the report shows and maybe will
with alternative ways to analyze such
data.
This is uh the scope of what we did for
version 27. We actually modernized all
the analytical reports uh that exist in
business central updating I think it's
seven of those and deprecating four. So
these four reports are no longer needed.
They are covered in other places of the
product either with data analysis and or
with a PowerBI app for sales.
If you want to learn more about do being
datadriven on the sales department or
the sales area uh the the landing page
sales analytics in our documentation you
can reach that from the aka link
aka.ms/bc
salesanalytics
and this landing page has personas
scenarios
uh and like artifacts that can help you
in the sales department.
So go check it out and see if you can
learn something that can help you like
improve uh performance profitability for
your sales department.
That's it. Just a few more minutes. If
you have seen this before, just skip
this section. If you are not already
following the product group on LinkedIn,
please do so. There's an AKA link here,
aka.ms/bcin.
uh follow us there to get weekly updates
on what's happening around the product
both now and uh things that are coming
in the future.
You're watching this on YouTube. We do
have uh and this is hosted on the
Business Central product team YouTube
channel that's uh available from
aka.ms/bc
YouTube. Um we host a lot of different
content there. these uh watch new
videos, but also co-pilot and AI videos,
tips and tricks, deep dives, and even uh
what we call under the hood uh videos
where we prior to a release, a couple of
months before we start releasing small
snippets of things that are coming uh so
you can kind of get a feeling of the
next version.
If you are a Microsoft partner, make
sure that you bookmark aka.ms/bcall.
That's the AKA link landing page for all
AKA links relevant for you. And if you
are a Microsoft partner for Business
Central and if you're not yet on Yammer,
please make sure that you join that
network. The aka link is aka.ms/bc
yammer. This is where a lot of the
conversations, questions around the
product happen in a environment where no
customers can see what you write. So
it's it's kind of a safe space. Uh so
make sure that you join that. If not,
you're missing out on a lot of
discussions and learnings and even
troubleshooting.
Um then the final part is both for
customers and for partners uh office
hours. So on a monthly basis we host
like 45 to 60 minute sessions on things
that are relevant in the future business
central different topics. So that aka
link aka.msbc
office hours is is showing you the the
upcoming program for the upcoming office
hours. So go join that. So with that,
thanks for watching. I hope you use some
of this uh sales analytics to uh to get
even more profitable and uh and drive
your business with data. Thank you.